welcome back uh can you guys show the
next item is number 16
5.16 it's a person pre yeah uh so as I
mentioned uh we're about
to start talking about uh the prayers
that we make to the medicine Buddha
gang of seven and a half
[Laughter]
Buddhas well the seven are traditional
and and shakim Muni is like
the the he's the manager of their group
it's like BTS and their manager okay so
uh so anyway uh we're gonna
be again there's an emphasis now in the
new soda of praying of including
yourself in the prayers and and just
that's all and it's a slight change in
your mental you know you know instead
of praying for the whole
world in fact uh I remember
uh uh when I did when you when you
graduate from Princeton you have to
write a thesis as an undergraduate you
have to write a thesis and uh two
thesises one junior year one senior year
and for my senior thesis I wrote uh
something about kopa who's a famous uh
uh scholar famous Buddhist
teacher and uh I wrote something about
his book and um the Perfection of
giving and then uh you have to do a uh
dissertation defense you get questioned
by your professors and it's very
frightening so you have to go into the
office and three of the professors from
your department will ask you questions
about about your thesis so I I went in
and I had my
defense and I remember I still remember
the the the the main question they asked
was uh when you when you do these
prayers in Buddhism do you also pray for
yourself you know when you do prayers
for all living beings doesn't include
yourself and you're and then you're like
oh yeah it does you know I am one of
those living beings so there's a big
emphasis in the
F of uh when you pray for all living
beings you you appreciate that you are
one of them are you the most important
of them no are you the least important
of them no you're kind of equal okay and
that's a refreshing thing to think about
okay so this pict piure was meant to
remind you uh when you do the prayers to
the medicine Buddhas this week in your
meditations and Tim told me you're
you're focusing more on on sort of
afternoon Retreat time and rather than
three days in the middle so during your
retreat time then um just don't forget
that when you pray for all living beings
there's one in your
room okay and they equal time equal
attention all right and and it's very
easy to forget that okay it's typical
for people to forget that but in this
sna it's really emphasized okay that you
are also there
something tell Teddy that
be okay
good just kidding all right uh next item
you
guys this is the order in which this is
this is the rest of the sna that we're
going to be doing this week okay and
that's all okay we're going to have in
treaties in treaty means please help me
okay in treaty means please help me okay
and we're going to go through the
medicine Buddhist in
disorder okay ocation means there's
6,000 people at the
stadium okay and you're going to do a
just a general prayer to all the Buddhas
and the bodh safas each Buddha has I
don't know 500 bodh safas it's about the
same as when you think about scale think
about the the same as that Stadium okay
and uh then we're going to have specific
in treaties uh and they're different for
each Buddha okay and they are different
requests for each Buddha and we're going
to be going through some of the main
ones in class so you can listen to them
in class and then you can do them when
you get home okay all
[Music]
right now I'm going to start mixing in
emptiness teachings okay and now I'm
going to start mixing in
ARA and his most famous book uh called
wisdom and
they're going to help you with your
sodna okay when you make the prayers to
the a Buddhist uh it's very important to
have an emptiness understanding okay so
here we go all right and by the way it's
difficult okay the book is difficult
loga is difficult and that's just the
way it is emptiness is not easy and
emptiness is not
uh it's not instinctive it it has to be
learned it's not something that people
naturally understand nobody nobody ever
did nobody ever will you need training
okay it's like learning to ride a
bicycle or something you need someone to
to teach you okay and uh so we're we're
going to have
specific exercises that thearer will
suggest for understand standing
emptiness but it takes it takes work it
takes some work you know okay okay and
here we go and it's not easy all right
and
um when I used to have trouble sleeping
in the monastery I used to read him his
poetry and it just put me to sleep right
away and so you know it's could save you
a lot of money on on sleeping pills and
stuff all right so uh here's the first
next it you
guys yeah
uh how different am I from one of these
Buddhas okay how different am I from one
of these Buddhist am I different from
them or am I somehow the same okay and
that's a big subject for neus
203rd I think chapter 22nd sorry yeah
22nd chapter okay we're on the 22nd
chapter which is called an investigation
of of what yeah t yeah someone who has
reached the goal okay it's an
investigation of Buddhas chapter 22 how
many chapters total 27
27 and the 20 second chapter that we're
starting with is an investigation of an
enlightened being what's an enlightened
being look like how are they what are
they made of and the first question here
is how am I different from an
enlightened Buddha okay what's the
difference between me and an enlightened
Buddha okay are we are we basically
different or are we basically the same
okay and we're going to go through this
question okay here's the
verse
uh and I you guys ready with the next
the next yeah uh I like
the we do have the Sanskrit of of Aran
Nar we have the original language that
he wrote
in uh I learned it from the Tibetan
translation which was done
about thousand years ago and um but
somehow the
Sanskrit is more poetic to me uh uh
because it's it's it's him writing it's
his original writing so uh
each time I give you a verse I will give
you the simple Sanskrit I call it
simplified
Sanskrit uh anglicized Sanskrit okay
easy for English readers to read okay
and I broke it up according to kind of
in a way that would be easy for English
speakers to pronounce okay uh but then I
also wanted to offer you the
chance to pronounce it correctly
and that's in the
second in the italics here that's the
actual uh exact pronunciation okay so
the first two lines is sort of like
normal English speakers
pronunciation and then the next two
lines is the
technical is how a an Indian how a
Sanskrit person would pronounce it okay
and uh so you can choose either one you
want okay if you want to recite these
vers verses or memorize them you can
choose anyone the third group pumo is
the Tibetan okay and that's the Tibetan
translation Tibetan translation is
normally two times as many lines as the
Sanskrit okay and then I have the
English translation which is sometimes
three times as long as the Sanskrit okay
English is not a economical language
Chinese is very economical okay okay Sun
anyway here we go I'm going to pronounce
it for good
luck correctly and then you're welcome
to pronounce it uh generally a general
pronunciation
[Music]
okay
sorry okay that's the Sanskrit
uh they are not their body and mind they
are not something else than their body
and
mind they have no body and mind they are
not in their body and
mind those G tagata right have no body
and mind where then are
they all right and this is very very
typical Neoga and
and many many generations have
misunderstood it okay many many okay
many many
people had ridiculous ideas about these
lines okay many many generations whole
Generations whole schools of
Buddhism didn't understand anything
about what he said and they made up
ridiculous things like you're not there
you don't have a body and mind you know
you should go sit in the
snow you know
really
neous wincing he like oh ow you know
like wow they really
misunderstood so I guess the thing you
can say about narina
is he's the greatest writer of emptiness
in history and he's the most
misunderstood writer of emptiness in
history okay and uh you have to to be
trained what he's talking about or you
will make a mistake okay he's not saying
you don't have any body and you don't
have any mind he's not saying that
uh and when you're reading theara okay
and it's one of
my it's one of the things I do with my
whole life is to read Nara you know I
just reading the go people say what's
your occupation people ask me on
airplanes what's what your occupation I
see I read
Nar and you know it's a lifetime thing
uh
and and once you know the keys it's not
difficult and you you will get a good
explanation and and we are in a
lineage it's on cop as lineage uh we had
some Copans um he's 100% correct and he
understood it perfectly and I don't
think maybe anyone ever has except him
okay so your that's your lineage okay
and and it's been passed down very very
very carefully very well okay I spent
all day with this stuff I spent uh three
days on Sha Ping's Monday night class I
spent three
days uh on on the one-hour
class and I mean I'm talking 12 14 15
hours on her one-h hour class and I
didn't finish yet uh I'm still working
on it and um it's it's extremely deep
and it's
extremely uh difficult your book is
interesting uh and we'll talk more about
it
Monday but uh she she translated a book
about Buddhist moral
uh
via uh of all the translators her book
is probably the oldest it's it is
exactly two and a half thousand years
old and
um and it's very difficult and uh it's
it's the
253 vows for monks and 364 vows for nuns
and all the other vows okay she had a
detailed commentary of over 600 vs and
it took us seven years to finish it uh
we will probably finish Monday
night okay
uh we're on the last page now whether
she can get through it I don't know but
uh it's very very deep and very
difficult and the language is very
ancient and um it's like reading China
chinesee from 3,000 years ago or
something it's very difficult to read
and we had
to we had to use John Brady's database
constantly uh and we had to consult
other books there's about
uh I don't know 50,000 pages of Vana
commentaries input by John Brady 50,000
pages and we have a search program we
can ask get a question in in one second
we can get an answer from 50,000 Pages
if we don't understand what a vow
there's a vow that nuns are not allowed
to wrap their spice packages in
thread so if you see Ellie doing
it let me
know and you know it comes from a story
of a a naughty nun
who was pretending that she couldn't
wrap her spice packets in thread so she
asked a handsome monk to help
her and uh but here's this whole story
we have no idea why is why aren't nuns
allowed to wrap their spice packages
with certain kinds of threads and every
time we had a
question we found the answer in a in
another book that was written uh 450
years ago and uh every time we searched
the database we kept hitting the same
book you know and then I said we should
translate that book you know and that's
a like a 30-year project it's a
huge
commentary by a a person who lived about
uh almost 600 years
ago and uh so here's the thing I was
studying uh getting ready for your book
because you might start the new book on
Monday night we don't know I think
so
uh and I studied all the times we found
our answers there and there's two books
it's not one book it's two books okay
the answers we found were in two
different books okay by the same person
and with the same
title and they're not the same
okay so for seven years every time we
had a question we searched the book uh
we searched we found all the answers in
this one book but it turns out to be two
books with the same
name and
Rewritten he he wrote
a he wrote a 8,000 page book and then he
rewrote
it which one you're going to translate
you know what are we gonna
do uh in this lineage what I'm trying to
say is this lineage is
extremely careful and uh the Gara is
presented
correctly and I don't think you will see
anywhere else I don't think you can find
it anywhere else and people always
coming to me you know I I met a teacher
in the airport he looks nice you know
and I'm
like you know I I don't mean to
criticize other Traditions I I really
don't
uh but but they're
wrong okay n 90% 99%
mistaken just mistaken it's like uh
teach you how to fix a car and you break
the car you know it's like that there's
a way to fix a car I tried my
teacher he's he here's my teacher 1970
six he's like my watch broke fix my
watch I'm like what he said fix my watch
you know I said well I don't know if I
can he said aren't you American I said
yeah I'm American he said it says Made
in America you know you fix it I said
look just because it's made in America
doesn't mean I know how to fix it you
know and he kept doing it he kept doing
it over and over again his car
broke you know his car broke he said fix
the car I said I have never touched a
car in my life I don't know anything
about cars he said teach
yourself and I
did uh I learned how to I took the whole
engine apart and uh I broke
it it never ran
again it
started it ran okay for like a day and
then it broke on the verono bridge this
one of the highest and longest bridges
in the United States it broke at the top
and uh anyway what I'm saying is it's
very similar to a car engine the
guardian is very similar to a car engine
it's it's very deep it's very complex
there's a correct way to read it and
everyone else every all the other ways
to read it are wrong and you will break
it and it won't work and it will hurt
you you'll be up at the top of the
bridge at
midnight
driving some llama back from Kennedy
Airport and it broke at the top and I
got out in the middle of traffic on the
highest bridge in New York at midnight
and there was a windstorm and I'm trying
to get the stupid car to work and I'm
saying the G is very similar there's
there's
a there's a correct thing he's saying
and then there's 99 things he's not
saying and and I have never seen any
other lineage that explains it correctly
so you know ask me I met a teacher in
the airport gisha he looks really nice
and I'm like yeah okay I mean but don't
ask me the details you know don't ask me
I mean if if they can teach you
emptiness uh because they can't and and
I I'll say it openly and I'll say it
frankly cannot and and they're nice and
they they could ring the bell at the
right place and that's okay but they
don't understand this okay I don't I've
never met one like that so this lineage
is is unbelievable and and I'm
not saying it out of loyalty I'm saying
it out of just if you know how to fix
this car the car will run and if you
don't know how to fix it you'll mess it
up and and I've seen it a thousand times
go and ask me about llas and in the
airport okay uh if they understand this
if they can explain it correctly then
yes uh they're they're a nice person but
uh
otherwise you cannot see emptiness
directly and you will suffer and you
will die so it's your choice okay and
and that's all and I'm sorry that's just
the way it is okay and and all the rest
is nice and I I love them and I I H hang
out with them and but they can't teach
you this you this and you need it to see
emptiness directly you need it if you if
you don't learn it you can't
okay and I I have to say that right I'm
like
a trust your Tesla to someone who can
fix a Tesla or don't take it to the
market
really okay I'm not saying because I
don't like the other card dealers I'm
just saying they can't f it okay all
right I I blew it up I know okay all
right here we go they are not their body
and mind they are not something else in
their body and mind uh we're going to go
to understand
that we're g to go to the real word here
in the Sanskrit is scanda say scanda
scand scanda means one of the five parts
of you okay scanda means one of of the
five parts of you uh I have translated
scand here as body and mind okay in
English we don't say hey Teddy you are
made of your F scas we say you have your
body and you have your mind you are your
body and mind okay we say that in
English we don't have the word five scas
okay what is
scanda scanda means uh one of your parts
okay in normal English we say body and
mind okay who are you you are the
combination of your body and mind okay
that's normal in
Buddhism we never say just body and mind
rarely we say you are your five scas
okay your five scas okay scanda is an
ancient word that
[Music]
means pile of
leaves pile of leaves like a big big
bunch of stuff okay like a whole pile of
stuff you know what did your bedroom
look like just before you left for the
airport piles of stuff everywhere some
of it made it into my suitcase most of
it's still there my family's dealing
with it you know there's piles of stuff
all over my room so in Buddhism we don't
say body and mind we say piles of stuff
okay your you are five piles of stuff we
don't say you are your body and mind we
don't say that okay uh but if you're
trying to
communicate to a normal English speaker
and you say are you your five piles of
stuff or not and then they're like what
maybe I did clean my room uh okay so
here I translated as body and mind okay
but I want to explain to you
you why Buddha didn't use body and mind
okay because you can't understand narina
if you don't
understand what he's saying you are
not okay he says you are not your body
and mind and the Buddha is not their
body and mind the medicine
Buddhas are not their body and mind we
are marrying theara to the medicine
Buddhas okay they were having a big
ceremony at the fire offering
we are doing a marriage by the way at
the fire offering but uh we're marrying
these two books okay the guardian is
explaining what the medicine buddh are
made of and and he's and if you don't
know what a medicine Buddhist made of
it's probably not going to work to pray
to the medicine Buddhist to help a sick
person for example okay to try to get
medicine Buddhist assistance to help a a
sick person with your medicine Buddha
practice but you don't know who they are
or where they are it probably won't work
okay if you understand who they are the
prayers will work if you don't
understand who they are they might not
work understand okay if you understand
how a Car
Works maybe you can fix it if you have
no idea how a car works I suggest you
take it to somebody else okay got it
okay I had the experience I blew up my
teacher's car there's a special feeling
when you blow up your teacher's
car and I'll never forget
it and he never asked me again to fix
this car which was the real uh goal I
had in know
okay
uh okay so next verse you guys and we'll
come back to this verse
uh uh can you just show that item can
you show the lady with the
brain yeah uh G Michael's having fun
with artificial intelligence uh my
particular computer specializes in
artificial
stupidity uh I call it as and other
things ass sometimes but it's a AI so I
said I I told the AI I need a lady with
a brain in her hand and he did pretty
good I think uh he does lots of weird
ones that I'm not going to show you my
wife finally she said stop asking me to
come see the funny mistakes that the AI
made she she refused one day she's in
the kitchen I said you gotta see this
one you know like she said I'm not
looking at your ai's mistakes anymore
just leave it you know but this one when
he did
okay
uh if in normal English and all over the
world you say body and mind right why in
Buddhism do you have to say those those
piles of stuff okay why why do you have
to say piles of stuff why why did Narin
say the medicine Buddhists are not their
piles of stuff and they're not not their
piles of stuff and they're not both not
and not
there piles of stuff okay why did he say
that why did he say piles of stuff okay
and I want to teach you about uh why in
Buddhism do we say piles of stuff and we
don't say body and mind okay and it's a
famous famous famous question and it's
answered in the Abid Dak kosha by uh
vasu
okay
um what is
it
that's the verse in okay why do we talk
about the five piles of stuff why don't
we talk about body and mind and he says
there is body and mind but you have to
split up the the Mind part okay you can
say body and mind that's okay and the
whole argument of
Nar can be you are not your body and
mind
but it's useful to split the mind up
okay it's useful to split the Mind part
up and then the question is why and he
says because it causes all your trouble
cway gu gu means there's certain parts
of your
mind that caused your your death death
Death deal
mortality the fact that you can die is
caused by certain parts of your mind
okay so we never say body and mind we
say body and the different parts of your
mind some of which can kill you okay
okay I'll say it again do we talk about
body body and mind yes do we ever call
it body and mind no what do you call it
body and the mind which includes Parts
in it which is going to kill you and we
every time we talk about you and every
talk time we talk about your body and
your mind we want to remind you that
there's time bombs in your mind that
will kill you and if you can get them
out you don't have to die okay you you
don't have to die so we never say body
and mind in Buddhism we say your body
and your your mind which includes Parts
which are going to kill you and then
hopefully people think well maybe I'll
get rid of those parts and yeah yeah
that's the that's why we don't say body
and mind thank you okay and so every
time we talk about your
parts every time we talk about who you
are we're not going to say uh you're
body and mind we're never going to say
your body and mind we're going to say
your body and your mind which includes
Parts which are going to kill you okay
and then hopefully one day you'll say
boy it' be nice to get rid of those part
you know and that's I don't know that's
why Lord Buddha
demanded that we don't say body and mind
we say body and the mind which includes
Parts which are going to kill you okay
so we don't have this lady we don't have
this body and mind she's supposed to
represent body and mind okay that's what
I asked the AI to make body and mind you
did
okay uh what's in her head I don't know
uh
but okay but there's parts of your mind
now what are those parts let's talk
about them okay and that's the next
verse you guys
ready VI
that's the Sanskrit okay
abos
uh very very famous why do we separate
out from all the mental functions how
many mental
functions 46 or 51 am I right 51 or 52
51 46 or 51 depends on what school
depends on what source you use okay
um of all the mental functions why do
we say two parts of your mind which
cause trouble okay why do we separate
out two parts of your mind okay out of
the 46 mental functions in Buddhist
psychology Buddhism has a very
sophisticated Psychology from 1,700
years ago much better better than modern
psychology actually uh but they say two
of the functions of your mind are
troublemakers two of the functions of
your mind actually precipitate your
death okay if you could fix them you
wouldn't have to die okay so here they
are uh of all the mental functions let's
take out feelings and discrimination
Your Capacity to feel and your capacity
to discriminate these are two of the
let's say 46 mental functions in the
Abid kosia okay these are two of the in
Buddhist
psychology the capacity to feel is
mental although you do it through your
body
sometimes okay in the capacity to
discriminate okay so
feeling your capacity of
feeling is divided into either three or
five feelings okay three is the easy way
it's good feeling bad feeling and in
between okay uh you can split the Bad
and the good into two you can say mental
or physical okay you could say good
physical feeling good mental feeling bad
physical feeling bad mental feeling and
then they say neutral and then somebody
says well why didn't you split neutral
into body and mind physical and mental
well it's so vague that it doesn't
deserve to be
split okay when you're
feeling when you're not aware of feeling
bad and you're not aware of feeling good
you tend to not think about how you're
feeling okay got it you know when you
feel too hot you feel when you feel too
cold you feel when the temperature is
like medium you don't notice it okay so
therefore we don't split neutral feeling
into two kinds okay we don't we don't
worry about it right the capacity to
feel is one of the fif of the 46 parts
of your mind which is causing all your
trouble the capacity to feel is one of
the 46 Parts in your mind which is
causing you all your trouble the other
one is your tendency to discriminate
okay this is good this is bad she's nice
she's not nice this is too hot this is
too cold I like this I don't like that
okay the capacity of discrimination
these are two mental
functions in the
Sanskrit
is kma
means uh there's a stepbystep process to
how these two mental functions cause you
trouble these two mental functions
of all the mental
functions in your mind
46 these two cause all of your problems
why then he says kma it's a stepbystep
thing it's a stepbystep thing what is
it uh they are the root of conflict and
they are the cause of sansar okay they
are the root of all conflict okay here
it is very easy all human conflict comes
from
discriminating this makes me feel good
and this makes me feel bad all human
conflict come from discrimination I like
this person I don't like this person
this person belongs to my Country and
this person belongs to your country and
discriminate I discriminate between the
two countries this is the root of all
conflict and that's based on feeling you
know I like people who eat the same food
as me and have the same color of skin
and I don't like people who eat other
kinds of food and have different color
skin okay that these two habits
discrimination based on feeling is the
cause of all conflict and of all sansara
it's the cause of all bad karma let
instead of referring to ourselves as
body and mind why don't we make an a
agreement
today whenever I ask you what's your
parts you're going to say the five parts
including two which cause all the
trouble okay and then hopefully if you
have to repeat it every day instead of
body in mind okay now you got to say
five P five piles of stuff two of them
are
trouble it hopefully you'll remember the
next time you have an argument with
someone or you see a person who is
different from you
different religion uh different Faith
different hair or no
hair uh you know hopefully if we don't
call you the culmination of your body
and mind and for the rest of your life I
call you the three good parts and the
two bad
parts uh hopefully you'll remember to be
careful with your discrimination okay be
careful with your discrimination okay
and it's very very very hard it wouldn't
be in the Abid
mosha if we all didn't do it okay we all
do it we all judge other people on their
skin color on the country they come from
on the food they eat on the language
they speak we all do it we all do it so
he says let's remind
ourselves every time we speak about body
and mind Buddha said I don't want you
talking about body and mind I want
talking about the five parts of you two
of which screw you up okay got it
forever we're going to talk about
now but when you're translating a class
and you know you you're translating
poetry especially I translated this for
the peacock parenting
class okay uh which hopefully be able to
see in a few months but they're they're
working on the videos we're going to
have one peacock parenting class here
this week because I I wasn't happy with
one class I want to redo it uh but I I I
translated this ver to use in dad class
because that class is based on poetry
it's how to be a good parent based on
World poetry okay which is a cool
concept I think uh we're gonna teach you
how to be a good parent based on poetry
and more than that a person who has
never been a parent is gonna teach the
class
okay it wasn't my idea all right I'm
just going along all right
uh so here's a new question for you okay
um why did Naran take the Buddhas for
this chapter of discussing the parts to
a
person why didn't he take just
anybody wh why didn't he say all human
beings are made of body and mind and
they are not their body and mind in the
way you think they are okay why didn't
he just say it that way why did he
choose Buddha body and mind
Sim because we think that Buddhas exists
self-existent as well
well here's the answer okay and it's
deep okay it's very deep all right it's
very deep and it's difficult okay
Buddhas are also made of body and
mind okay Buddhas are also made the
medicine
Buddhas are also made of body and mind
the medicine buddas I need a
Sharpie uh anybody have a sharpy or a
pen pen with a top on
it can I borrow it thank you oh that's
best I like
Sharpies okay uh mind and body okay body
and mind okay so Buddhas are made of
their body and mind if you're Abid
Dharma school this has you know
different parts two of them cause you
trouble but we're just talking normal
English body and mind okay Buddhas are
body and mind before they became a
Buddha were they body and
mind yeah so Buddhas are are made of
their body and
mind and normal people are made of their
body and mind he doesn't talk about
normal people in this chapter he says
those gone thus
tagata it means Buddhas okay enlightened
beings they are not their body and
mind and he doesn't talk about normal
people but do you have a body and mind
before you become a Buddha do you have a
body and mind after you become a
Buddha are you before you become a
Buddha are you B are are you your body
and
mind is this top and this bottom the
pen I I'll tell you when you teach this
this thing when you say is this saying
is this is the top and the bottom the
pen and somebody says no Then you say
come here I'll give your mustache you
know and they're like ew no especially
if it's a lady you say come here
somebody says the pen is not the top and
the bottom together and I said oh really
so it's not a pen and they said no I
said come here I'm going to put a
mustache on your face and like No And I
said come on it's almost
Halloween they're like no no then you do
believe it's a pen you really do believe
it's a pen don't tell me you don't
believe it's a pen you won't let me put
that body and mind on your upper Lim you
know you must believe it's a
pen only one person let me do the
mustache it was a guy in
Florida so anyway is the pen the top of
the pen in the bottom of the
pen so it's not a chew
toy
right huh didn't say that is it is it a
pen oh yeah good to whom now now you did
change your answer okay to you have to
say to whom okay is it is it to whom
okay you ready is a Buddha their body
and mind
good to whom okay let's do it again you
ready is a Buddha their body and their
mind then you have to say to whom okay
and that's the correct answer okay to
say they
are or to say they are not is incorrect
okay just and by the way in a
deban
uh if the question could be
misinterpreted you are required to ask
for a clarification I'll say it again in
a in a debate if the question is a trick
question and it could be answered in two
ways you fail as a as a Defender if you
don't ask for a clarification okay is a
Buddha their body and
mind yeah to whom okay that's that in
the debate that's called clarifying the
question if if you failed to clarify the
question you lost the debate already
because both answers are
correct no and yes are both correct is
this is this top and bottom a
pen to yeah to whom if you say yes
you're wrong and if you say no you're
wrong okay got it that's the key of
ngara poetry here is a Buddha there is a
Buddha their mind and their body yeah to
whom what what's that say for
$100 what's that say about the process
of not being a Buddha and then becoming
a
Buddha I'll drink orange
juice you're you're
correct she has Le ginus which makes her
a great debater today
and protection Miss wi has yeah
learn yeah that's all uh it's coming
from from the perceiver okay is a Buddha
there body and
mind to whom
yeah to a person who has the seeds to
see a
Buddha yeah they are okay got it okay
even themselves even to themselves are
they of
Buddha so that applies to people who not
Buddha yet right is a person who's not a
Buddha yet a person who's not a Buddha
yet yeah to whom beautiful beautiful
people nice yeah is a person who's not a
Buddha yet their body and their
mind the combination of their body and
mind is a person who's not a
yet the combination of their body and
mind yeah and you have to say to whom
okay to whom if you see a person in that
body and mind it's coming from from you
okay it's the same as the pen okay let's
go back to the verse and see if it makes
sense okay Buddhists are not their body
and mind make
sense the medicine Buddhas that you are
asking for help are not their mind and
their body yes or no yeah they're not so
far we can say they're not okay because
I'm saying to nobody right are they
something other than their body and mind
are they rocks and plants or
something to whom yeah yeah yeah and
there's many cases of people meeting a
Buddha as a tree or as a bridge or as a
song okay uh like that all right uh they
they correct L perceive a a song as a
Buddha or they correctly perceive their
children as a Buddha you know okay so
are Buddhist their body and
mind I don't know we can't say yet are
they something else than their body and
mind we can't say yet do they have a
body and
mind we can't even we can't even say now
the second part here is called The Raw
data question the second part here is
called the RW data question okay what's
raw data
question
uh is this a
pen yeah to whom uh is this a black
cylinder and is this a a white
cylinder yeah to whom you have to keep
saying to whom okay even the parts in
the highest School of Buddhism by the
way who who invented the high school
Buddhism n
well traditionally we say nar okay the
highest teachings of emptiness the the
the founder is considered Nar okay uh do
Buddhist have a body and
mind he says they don't have a body and
mind the raw data of a Buddha the top
and the and the body of a pen these all
also depend on who's looking okay it's
not a top of a pen by itself and it's
not a bottom of a pen by itself and the
two together the two together are not a
pen by itself I understand that's easy G
the dog choose it I understand that but
doesn't the dog see a black cylinder and
and the human and the and the human also
sees a black cylinder and a white
cylinder what about a blind
person okay what about a blind person
you see what I mean even the white color
even the black color even the raw data
of Human Experience is coming from you
also okay you made the bottom of the pen
and you made the top of the pen and you
made the white and you made the black
okay it's coming from your mental States
Buddha's second part here have no body
and
mind okay and they are not inside their
body and mind you can look at the top of
the pen you can look at the bottom of
the pen for the rest of your life you
won't find a pen can it be a
pen yeah if the person has the seeds to
see it as a pen and to get a mustache
therefore okay then yeah you can see it
as a pen but from its own side is it a
pen no it's not or else you couldn't
chew a dog couldn't chew on it okay got
it so does the poem make sense so
far yeah is a Buddha their body and mind
I don't know I don't know yet give me
more information are there something
else in their body and mind I didn't to
say that I mean there could be you know
do they have a body in mind I don't know
depends on who's looking I mean lots of
people can't recognize a sacred tree as
a Buddha or their children as a Buddha
or their dog some guy told me my root
llama is my dog is that okay I'm like if
you see him that way that's all right
you know okay it really is all right
okay and it really is true it's okay
they they have no body in mind they are
not inside their body and mind we're
okay so far
right let's go to the last
one those gone does have no body and
mind true or
false they do have a body and mind of
course they have a body and mind I
didn't say they didn't have a body in
mind yeah you did you just said they
have no body in mind I said they have no
body in mind I didn't say well those
guys don't does have no
body okay got it to themselves in their
own perceptions they have a body and
mind I didn't say they didn't they do
got it you okay everybody okay it's a
pen thing just keep remembering the pen
thing so where are the
Buddhas where are the buddh where are
the medicine bus yeah when you invite
them you're inviting them from your own
mind
okay when you invite a medicine Buddha
to come and negotiate that your uncle's
cancer will go away right where do they
come
from they're coming from you okay
they're coming from you if a Buddha is
coming from you is it true that they
can't
work no G's the opposite the only way
they can work is if they are coming from
me me okay wait but you're not a Buddha
and you're making
Buddha yeah no problem I got hot seeds
today
okay okay got it you're not a Buddha but
you can make a Buddha yeah that's no
problem I'm not a Buddha but I have the
seeds to have medicine Buddha come when
I asked them to come to the stadium and
I set up all the chairs uh medicine
Buddha arrives okay got it are they
coming from
you did you make
them can they still do things for you
that you cannot do for
yourself yeah got it beautiful you guys
are well trained by
somebody and I appreciate your teachers
by the
way
no
uh we used to have five students okay in
19 I don't know 05 or something 19 what
year was that
1993 in 1993 when ACI started 30 Years
Ago by the way we're gonna have 30th
anniversary in Koto okay but uh we had
five students okay I had five students
okay now uh it's about 200,000 okay
uh DCI itself is about 150 something
thousand people okay and uh and I'll
tell you this morning's email
account
59,6 72 unread emails okay
59,6 72 unread emails so people who knew
me 20 years ago 30 years ago they're
like Gish can I just talk ask you a
question I'm like yeah except there's
aund and there's a there's 200,000 of
you now and then and then I I I feel
frustrated and I feel uh exhausted and I
feel uh I feel hurt that people don't
understand you know I said do the math
you're an engineer suang you have a he
has an engineering degree from
England uh let's do the
math
uh what is it uh
200,000 times five I just need five
minutes which is always a
lie is uh a million a million minutes
divided by
60 it's uh 177,000 hours if I give five
minutes to everybody and and and I'm not
complaining I spent my whole life to
create those 200,000 people you know I'm
happy I feel a lot of Happiness about
that I it took me 50 years to create
200,000 students but I don't have time
to talk talk eachone for five minutes
it's totally impossible I will die
you'll kill me
so I have a list of very qualified
teachers and if you ask them a question
and if you ask me a question I guarantee
you you're going to get the exactly the
same
answer okay I mean if you just think I'm
more handsome than
Tim that's
true uh but
otherwise I trained them some of them
for 30 years you know and if they don't
give you the same answer I'll fire them
okay so and I'm not saying I don't enjoy
I love to talk to people I I grew up in
a big family I enjoy people I really
enjoy people so I mean and I'm not
saying don't stop me and ask me a
question it's okay go ahead take a shot
you know if I get grumpy you understand
why but but I have a list of people in
here who will give you exactly the same
answer okay uh Rebecca where can you
stand
up I don't know she's been my student
since she was a teenager
she still looks like a
teenager uh I'm kidding how old were you
when when
21 okay she was a college student yet in
New
York uh Venable Jigme venerable Ellie
can you stand up okay
[Applause]
yeah 25 years 30 years 30
years more than 30
years 30 30 years and uh 25 years she's
been my personal assistant so thank you
for that
uh
gy how long many 27 27 years W if she
don't give the same answer I'll fire her
Rob
haery how many years 27
27 okay by the way he's doing a lot of
the he's also taking some of the
personal assistant work because it's too
much now okay when Ellie started as my
personal assistant I had 10
students now I have 200 ,000 so I I'm
expanding my capacity by
100% And you know if you need personal
stuff they both they both can help okay
all
right
gam
[Applause]
right she's a
baby 1 13 years okay and she she's
sharper than the other ones so she can
give the same answer after only 13 years
okay but uh very great te these are all
great teachers okay uh Tim
[Music]
lenal he's a total
baby 13 years okay
okay all right uh cat Venable cat
[Applause]
C huh 20 years 20 years whoa
okay I remember the first me I had just
got out of threee retreat and she was uh
walking down the
desert Gully you know I said are you cat
she's like yeah and I said I have work
for
you right did I have work for you
okay uh andriana where are
[Applause]
you how many years 26
26 okay so don't say I can't teach a
parenting
course
Ina
[Applause]
Ina and her her husband Bill
McMichael I'll let you count it
together 23 years 23 okay cool yeah okay
good
combined uh they all studied yeah um um
also Angelie is here too Angeli
hi
Angelie how many
years oh baby
okay
uh B they have all studied vajana okay
they have all studied Diamond way it
takes a long time you know I taught a
seven-year ACI course and it was
required to to take the vadana course so
18 courses it's about 20,000 pages of
translation each page cost me many
hours and then uh seven years of Vrana
okay which is is 30,000 pages of
translation it's the best budri course
in history in in the last 2,000 years
okay I I'm sure I believe it and uh then
you you need
to you can ask them questions about
Diamond way okay and and I did not let
them start Diamond way until they
finished the 18 Foundation courses I I I
cheated on a few people
a few people they were really smart
really
handsome and uh you know and I thought
oh okay you don't have to do the whole
18 Foundation courses and they
failed okay and it wasn't a regular
failure it was a grand
explosion okay so I don't do it anymore
you know I I ask you finish your 18
courses okay it's for your benefit also
you will mess up yourself if you don't
do the 18 courses first you know then I
I said that in one guy whose name I
won't
mention he got all the answer keys of
the 18
courses and he copied them out in one
weekend which is itself he should get
credit H because it's 30,000 you know
pages of Stu and uh so anyway um you
know it was designed trying to take six
or seven years for the 18 courses if you
want to work through them faster than
that I I don't really mind I I guess you
could do it in four years five years if
you really work hard but part of the
idea of taking seven years was that uh
you would
mature uh your thinking would mature and
your you would get older and you would
have more life experiences and and you
would change in those seven years
whether I teach you or not in those
seven years you will change okay you'll
grow up and I have to say these 18 20 30
year
olds they were not like that when they
got
here okay and it was a long hard process
of growing up and uh you know it takes
time you you can technically try to copy
out all the an tur kees in in in two
years or something but you're just
cheating yourself okay you won't have a
good experience in the Diamond W so so
you know relax it's the best
courses in history and don't rush
through them and you know if there's a
long homework just relax and do it okay
and uh have fun and don't think I'm
trying to cheat you out of a year or
something
you know don't cheat yourself okay take
the time it takes everybody's in a big
rush to get to vajana and then they
don't do the homeworks and when they get
the vaj they say what's the big deal you
know and they and they fail so so do it
the way Grandpa intended
it uh I mean the the generally it was a
14e experience okay and whether you
studied for those 14 years or you don't
study for those 14 years inevitably you
grow up during those 14 years okay
whether you have a course or not so uh
that's my experience all right and but
these people have uh experience they
they've done the time you know and they
for every one of them there's there's 10
or 20 people who disappeared okay and um
so you know ask them questions you don't
have to ask me you're going to get the
same answer from them trust me okay I
train them I know
okay all right Tim where are we are
we so five minutes yay do I go direct to
my
nap no uh okay any any questions from
the audience online
Maybe we have 200,000
students it's not possible for me to do
what I did 10 years ago or 20 years ago
and
please please recognize that it's not
that I'm mean or I don't want to talk to
people it it's true but uh I no I really
really enjoy people those people who
know me you know I enjoy people and I
just it's physically I can't do it so
okay all right next
yes okay loud LNA okay LNA yeah I'm
sorry I'm I'm probably the foolest
person in this room because I know it's
a lot of professionals here and I'm a
brand new okay good for a year I try to
every day I promise myself to Hur about
to listen you about the pen wow every
morning I'm sorry I don't get it I try
to explain everyone I try to explain my
R yesterday and I'm I'm so confused even
more and more so I don't know if it's
like seeds or it's my foolish brain or I
have no idea but honestly I'm so sorry I
don't get it okay let's do the pen real
fast please please
[Applause]
uh by the way uh when I invented the
pen by the the the classical example is
a white Kell
from the
ocean that's the classical example uh
and I chose a pen the logic was that
everyone's always got a pen in their
pocket but that was before cell
phones uh so I don't but cell phones
don't work so good because dogs are not
interested in uh so I don't know I'm
going to stick with the pen for a while
but it it's losing its relevance like we
got to find something uh
anyway
and it's it's not a silly example and
it's not philosophy it's just truth okay
it's just the way it is when a dog looks
at this they don't see a pen right I
mean it's it's not a big philosophy
thing when a dog looks at this they
don't see a pen what do they
see chw
toy and a human sees a pen who's correct
yeah and and that
proves that the thing is coming from
from them if a dog sees a chw toy it
must be coming from them because if it's
coming from itself the human will see a
chw toy right logically and by the way I
mean the logic is undisputable you
cannot argue with it I never I mean I
had the one guy in Florida but that
doesn't count um uh I never had anybody
disagree does it does it look like a pen
to the human yeah does it look like a
chew toy to a young puppy who likes to
Che things yeah it does are they correct
yeah yeah and they're correct because of
the function a human can write with it
and a dog can chew on it get some
pleasure out of it therefore for them
it's a real chew toy for them it's a
real pen okay now listen please and I'll
say it a 100
times
uh it has to be coming from its side
right it has to be coming from me
somehow it has to be why because the dog
doesn't see a pen the dog sees something
else okay it please please please please
please understand one
thing it has to be true it's not me it's
not philosophy it's not Buddhism it's
not Buddhism it's just true okay does a
dog say Choy yeah does a human see a pen
then that chw toy and that pen must be
coming from the dog and must be coming
from the human that's all it's very
simple that the pen is not coming from
the pen
if the pen was coming from the pen the
dog would see a pen and the dog doesn't
see a pen therefore the pen is not
coming from the
pen okay it's coming from me somehow you
can say somehow and then the dog seees
they see the same thing and they want to
chew on
it listen please please please
listen if the dog sees a chew toy and if
the human human sees a pen then the
whole world is coming from
you and you you can't deny it you you
there's no argument in any language in
any philosophy in any human being
there's nothing you can say you can't
prove it wrong it must be coming from
you if the dog sees one thing and the
human sees a different
thing then everything's coming from you
must be must be must be that's all be
careful when you say when I ask you is
this pen coming from you be careful
before you go like that because this
means every I ever met was was
coming from me okay every dictator every
murderer every
warmonger you know every nuclear bomb
maker came from one
place you
okay all right cool and then if you want
to fix it there's only one thing you can
fix okay and that's Buddhism that the
pen is
Buddhism the pen itself is Buddhism you
don't need any other
Buddhism okay you can't blame anybody
for anything if the pen is
true and logically it's true you cannot
blame a single other person for anything
everything's your fault okay
but every beautiful thing is also coming
from
you yeah every beautiful person you ever
met every sunset at Diamond Mountain I
keep getting photos of the Dawn at
Diamond Mountain from cat because I'm
never awake to see
it but uh all you also created all the
beauty in the world every beautiful
person you created Lord
Buddha uh you created all the happiness
in the world you you yourself gave birth
to every kid in the world including my
granddaughter and uh you know so there's
a lot of Joy there too okay if if if the
pen is coming from you and and listen
no one can deny it no one in the world
no one can prove that this is not coming
from you no one it's not provable cannot
prove it it must be coming from you
because of the dog
thing then the world is in your hands
then the future of the world is in your
hands don't complain about bad people
you made
them okay then change them to fix them
you're the only one who can you're the
only one who can stop blaming other
people okay Gua does that mean I
shouldn't sty to try to stop a bad
person when they're trying to kill
somebody I didn't say that okay if
there's a bad person trying to kill
somebody and they're coming from your
seeds and it takes 10 years to fix those
seeds stand up in front of them and take
the bullet you know resist them try to
stop them without hurting them
okay or else you create more bullets you
see so okay but I didn't say because
it's coming from you you shouldn't try
to stop it you should try to you have to
okay you should do something if there's
refugees running around without a place
to stay without bombs coming down give
them a place to stay and ask your
friends to help you pay for
it
okay all right that's it Tim right thank
you